this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at SC - radio dotnet SC radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software as a software engineer chances
are you've crossed paths with MongoDB at
some point whether you're building an
app for millions of users are just
figuring out a side hustle as the most
popular non-relational database MongoDB
is intuitive and incredibly easy for
development teams to use now with
MongoDB Atlas you can take advantage of
MongoDB flexible document data model as
a fully automated cloud service MongoDB
Atlas handles all the costly database
operations and admin tasks you'd rather
not spend time on like security high
availability data recovery monitoring
and elastic scaling try MongoDB Atlas
for free today
visit MongoDB comm slash cloud to learn
more
[Music]
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Simon cross sleep and
today I'm very pleased to say my guest
is Josh long josh is spring developer
advocate pivot or Java champion and
prolific within the Java community he's
previously hosted software engineering
radio and currently a host of both a
beautiful podcast and sprint tips videos
he's co-author of six books on Java and
spring and an instructor on my lessons
training videos so Josh thanks for
taking time from your busy schedule and
welcome to software engineering radio
thank you very much this makes team
pleasure thanks for having me
awesome and where does spring boot fit
in that what what is the kind of mission
statement of spring boot great so in
that ecosystem right and so we realized
that spring was a very flexible solution
but it wasn't necessarily a very
opinionated solution we had a we'd had a
go at something called spring Roo which
was in an opinion
approach to spring but it was it was
based on the idea of code generation and
by the time we got to 2013 it it we
didn't really need code generation we
could do all the things that we wanted
to do at encode right without actually
having to synthesize that code we were
we yeah and we could get the effect of
code generation by doing them by
generating classes right we can actually
complete compile or pre generate two
classes they get loaded by the class
owner so it's not even reflection it's
just dynamically generated classes that
run just like you know the class was run
so there's this there's this incredible
opportunity and we wanted to be able to
support certain kinds of applications
applications that would run in a cloud
environment and this was all
contemporaneous with a pull request r/a
JIRA issue that landed on the spring
framework JIRA years ago saying hey we'd
like some support for running spring in
an in an embedded web container right so
rather than deploying a dot war into a a
an Apache Tomcat or something like that
let's let's use embed it like embedded
jetty standalone jetty that we can just
public static void main into a server
how do I deploy spring into that and at
first we thought well this will be a low
hanging kind of thing and turned out
quite the contrary there's actually a
whole host of issues that come up when
you try and do that
and that began this discussion that
turned into you know the spring boot
right that that that process took more
than a year so they the way that
enterprise applications always used to
be developed with your back in the day
uh Vijay B's was you needed an
application container yeah and spring
boot is embedding the container within
it's its own jar file right yeah that
that that's a big change what what drove
that change ah very good point you know
I had even thought about that that's
true the original sort of use case the
original sort of revolution here and
with spring was to say ok well rather
than depending on this critical
infrastructure inside this giant
unwieldy application server I'll control
as much of that logic in my code proper
as possible and eventually with spring
boot we took that one step further
to control the webserver that was sort
of a last bastion of like things on
which on which we depended in a typical
application server right because the
last last thing in that in the
application server layer that we still
depended on that we didn't control
ourselves the the the thing that drove
our use of spring in the application
server world was to say we want to be
able to control our the reason that we
want to control our code the reason why
when I have a hand in how our
application behaves at runtime and not
be in a situation where we depend
entirely on this application server to
make our application whole right that
was the situation that before you would
have to deploy these incomplete class
files these are classes that would be
deployed into the application server and
it would be managed by the lifecycle of
that application server you couldn't
easily test this code without the
application server because they didn't
mean anything without the application
server and that meant that you were at
the whim of the life cycle of the
application server so if it was slow and
particularly you know Burton's him to
spin up a new instance and we deploy and
refresh and all that stuff then you were
just had to wait right very very painful
so spring embeds the application server
we but we embed the application
container and we can do a lot of things
one spring controls the application
container
whereas application servers don't
typically introduce new features outside
of the band you know out-of-band of the
specification life cycle spring could
deliver all sorts of new stuff so we
were very quickly able to reach parity
with what any application server could
do and then that was 15 years ago right
and now it's now ever since then it
we've just added new features right well
I'm sure there's a knob or a widget on
some application server that spring
doesn't support but generally all the
things that you want to do many of
transactions exposed web services talk
to databases message queues that kind of
stuff all that all the big sort of check
boxes right so by embedding the
application server inside your
application you've got something that
has fewer dependencies it's better
isolated and it's easier to to develop a
test and deploy if you're packaging all
that stuff in easy have you lost any
flexibility you used to be able to
package an application and then the idea
was it was portable yeah we tied to one
specific application can
okay so I don't know that we've got less
dependencies I suppose you you could so
the nice thing about spring is that it's
in the a la carte kind of thing right
you can choose you can you know use what
you you can pay for what you use so you
if you just want to build a web app
great then just bring in the dependency
that allows you to build web apps and
spring will support you in that context
if you want to build a web app that
talks to a to a sequel data store then
great you know bring in JPA or mybatis
or the java Oh cue juke or or just raw
JDBC template which simplifies JDBC
programming all these are fine options
in that context or or the new spring
data RTD BC which is for reactive
programming right so you can bring in as
you like support for different
intubations and your your dependencies
then we'll grow accordingly but you're
not you know you don't have one single
monolithic dependency it used to be that
you had the application server and if
the application server provided what you
want great if not then you had to fight
the classpath of the application server
and make sure that you can add your own
dependencies so you had you had your
dependencies spread across two different
logical sort of domains you've got your
code and its application dependencies
and then the application server itself
and you need both in order for any
application to work now you've just got
one discussion what apps what
dependencies does my spring app depend
on because when you write code with
spring the original one of the big
original innovations one of the big
original sort of changes are you know
dismantling of the existing status quote
was that spring gave you this
application context it's just it's just
a big old bag of beans with I like to
say it's a it's a container that
contains your objects and when I say
objects I mean truly just any kind of
object right it's just these are just
regular old objects these are called
pojos right we talked about pojos this
is I think I think we're the first to
really popular is that term this idea of
a plain old Java object and the reason
we that we have to have that term over
there and it may seem simple it may have
seemed ridiculous but at the time people
were accustomed to deploying things into
application servers and these were very
weird it was very weird
these are mutant classes they they
extend that if you look for example EJB
to write each of III is markedly better
but look at HEB too
on average you'd have at least three
different interfaces you had to
implement not to mention a bunch of
others they'd have to generate or code
you write it got to the point where if
you're doing everything right you could
easily have five or six different
classes that weren't your business
object just to adapt that type to the
runtime expectations of your application
servers EJB environment and so these
weren't regular java objects these were
like these are monstrous these are
things that required yes that gave
nothing and they took away to all sorts
of time and complexity so whether it
added complexity and they took away time
so we would coined this idea of hey just
write an object why are the object up as
you would any other object in good old
object-oriented fashion and the
relationship that these objects have we
can express using a dependency injection
container we can say here's how these
things fit together I'm gonna write code
that depends on a data source the
definition of which I'll keep external
from that external to that code to that
object I don't want my dependency being
hard-coded in each single class so they
put another way the work of resource
initialization and acquisition we we we
extricate from any one particular class
we centralized it into a configuration
in spring and then we can easily inject
that reference wherever it's needed but
you are still wiring up your objects and
you're doing so at first in the you know
back then it was a textual
representation of your of your object
graph and the reason we did text is
because there were no annotations at the
time right Java five hadn't come out
there's no way to provide metadata about
your objects in the Java code itself you
have to do so externally and the benefit
of that is because it is that when you
are wiring up drugs between the telling
spring how to wire up your objects it
now has a perspective on how your thing
how your objects fit together and it can
interpose itself in between the the
scenes of your objects accrue object
graph that can say oh you wanted this
thing that's a POJO that's just a
regular old object with methods you want
that that thing to start and stop at a
transactional boundary you know to
demarcate a transactional boundary upon
invoking a method on that object right
so you've got a service and you want you
know container managed transactions
right well that's a thing that's pretty
interesting that came from egb
that was a it was a arguably much more
difficult to config
but it was there right it's very
interesting novel feature and so if
you're using a JB's that's a nice thing
you can enjoy is just commit container
manage transactions so what about
abstracting out that same mechanism what
about doing the same thing for spring
but not doing it so in a way that it
only works for transactions we want we
want to the ability to add to advise or
to so arguments your objects to do these
interesting things like container
mansions actions and security
propagation and whatever else in a
generic way right so spring can do that
because it has visibility into this just
object graph of yours so I've got an
amazing wealth and features available to
me as a as a developer with the Spring
Framework
everything's managed as Pocho so that
they're lightweight and easy to test and
I can I can assemble them in ways that I
want and I can pull in all these extra
dependencies to handle the enterprise
features that I need like databases and
message queues WebSockets and streams so
you know I've got a lot of capabilities
to play with at the at the beginning you
talked about you know consistent ways of
delivering key applications how does how
to spring boot help simplify this wide
array of possibilities and complexities
to make life simpler for developers
that's a great question with what we've
always tried to do is to find ways to
plug in new functionality without
foreclosing on the opportunity that
somebody else might use the underlying
mechanism to be the same thing in a
different way right so case in point I
just talked to you about this sort of
generic augmentation of classes right
the mechanism that we used behind the
scenes there something called aspect
oriented programming aspect oriented
programming is an idea that we kind of
nurtured and fostered from academia that
we've been sort of made enterprise-ready
and it's a it's a I don't think most
people deal with AOP today in 2019 but
it it's still there and it's very much
what allows us to do what we do in a
generic way it's a way of saying I want
to match a
particular pattern and that pattern is a
pattern that describes for example you
know a method is invoked or a field is
set or a constructor is invoked
something something very generic you can
say on these events whenever this thing
happens and I'm describing this in the
school in what's called a point cut
expression then call this method or call
this object invoke this object in some
way give this object a chance to to be
aware of the fact that you're calling a
method and possibly even change what
happens to that method on its invocation
by giving it access to the parameters of
that method giving it access to the
return value of the method etc that
mechanism sounds kind of a well it
sounds very weird I think if you haven't
seen or seen it work it before but in
practice that allows us to build very
interesting things like I said like we
can we can we built a container manage
transaction management with that
fundamental technology but you could -
now as my point it wouldn't it wouldn't
be that hard because we had this AOP
foundation we exposed the mechanism that
we use to teach the Spring Framework new
features new tricks there's other
obviously have to write api's and all
that stuff but the the way we can
introduce that that functionality into
your code in a way that's kind of a just
declarative right for you you don't have
to change your code and have to extend a
bunch of types and so on the way we do
that is through a opie when it came to
spring but-- we we realized that a opie
there's three different there were sort
of three different pillars to a typical
spring application there's a portable
service abstraction that is to say the
the API is on which your application
depends that support different use cases
like for example talking to it a sequel
data store yeah and you know that's well
supported by something like the JDBC
template or or whatever there's the
there's a dependency injection that's
this idea that you have a container that
has an understanding of the relationship
of the objects in your applications
object graph and it can let let you
write code in terms of you know simple
interfaces and then you get a at runtime
you get a ready-to-use
ready to initial already already
initialized instance of that object so
you keep your code clean of any
particular explicit dependencies which
by the way promotes testing right so I
take my object that was written for a
job except sequel that data source at
runtime I can give the thing a pointer
to a reference to a a PostgreSQL you
know I carry CP managed connection pool
that's intern managing a PostgreSQL data
data source I can do that at runtime but
in my test I can just use a mock because
the code was written in such a way that
just it just expects job except sequel
that data source and my code isn't aware
of the specific variants right sex
dependency injection and then we've got
a AOP and at aspect-oriented program
those are the that we when we first
talked about spring we talked about that
triangle the three pillars of what makes
the spring up work and I think the big
revelation in spring boot is to add
another corner there so now we've got
more like a square and that corner is
something called Auto configuration Auto
configuration is the thing that allows
your application to its if you
appreciate that there are there are
different ways to pull together your
objects to do something then you can
understand that that is you know each
time you add a new library each time you
add a new feature to spring each time
you add you know the JDAMs support or
the RabbitMQ support of the kafka
support or you add the servlet support
or the reactive web flex support each
time you add a new feature to a spring
application there's a corresponding
amount of configuration that needs to be
done you need to you need to wire up the
embedded web server you need to wire up
a connection factory for the for to talk
to JMS you need to wire up your data
source to use the JDBC support there's
all this configuration and a lot of that
looks the same from one app to another
right we don't want people spending
their time recreating this code and and
at first we favored flexibility we said
we give you the ability to be explicit
about how these things are wired
together as opposed to what you could
have expected back it back in the time
back at the time with an application
server an application server did you
know five tricks let's just say I'm sure
to you know let's say twenty tricks okay
it did twenty tricks at the time it's
different now but it did twenty tricks
but that was it if you'd if you wanted
to do something else you were completely
on your own you have to start from all
from from the from the bottom up right
it did those 10 to 20 tricks very well
but outside of that there was no
to add a new trick to the application
server you just had the right code in
your application with spring are the
number of tricks we can do is virtually
limitless because we you know it's the
same kind of stuff if you want to write
if you want to use one of these features
you just create the objects that then
instantiate these features and that got
that gets to be tedious after after a
while you get to see that the
flexibility gives you flexibility that
then the sort of possibility there is it
is interesting but I think a lot of
people have you know being being
brutally honest there there's a lot of a
lot of apps are very very similar you
know how I configure my my application
in 2019 when I build a web-based
application it looks basically the same
I need support for you know JSON and XML
marshaling I need support for rendered
views I need support for you know form
binding and validation you know all
these kinds of things and and if there's
some exception to that I'll let you know
right but I but it you can go ahead and
just give me the absolute sort of
commonplace default and I'll and I'll
work with that and that's this sort of
that that came from I think the we all
would debt of gratitude to the Rubin
rails community for giving a society of
a convention over configuration right
but with Ruby rails you again with Rubin
rails and with the application servers
you got convention over configuration
but if you wanted to undo those
conventions you were in trouble because
either as in the case with as it was the
case with the application server
there was nobody up and do it you
couldn't like just use part of an
application servers EGP functionality
right you you couldn't just use the
engine underneath the ETV server and use
that for transaction management or
sometimes that right that's not actually
a good example because you could have to
do that but you couldn't do you couldn't
extract parts of the application server
and just use part of it you couldn't
just turn some things off and whatever
sending for Ruby rails in the beginning
right a lot of that was code generation
and it generated code and there were
some small toggles and knobs and levers
here and there but generally you were
stuck with what you got right there was
not it wasn't gonna just it wasn't gonna
do something differently a radically
different it was optimized for a
particular use case so we wanted to have
that same velocity that you get with
convention without sacrificing the the
flexibility because
that's one of the things that spring is
so good at is is serving these other use
cases that aren't served by the eight by
the eighty percent so we found writing
an app and you know I turn it's a
RESTful API and I'm gonna use a database
then you know if I if I choose my
Postgres database then spring boot will
detect that I'm using Postgres and both
the appropriate drivers and wire them up
in the in the default way so that the
database is ready to use these is that
how it works sort of I mean very close
so we have this thing it like I said we
have this thing called Auto
configuration what that Doug what that
is is just a bunch of configuration it's
just you it's just it's a class that
contains the definitions for objects
that will be useful to you in a
particular context so suppose you are
using a Postgres database and you've got
the or rather you're using a sequel data
store you've committed to that and so as
such you have the requisite JDBC
dependencies and the rig and you have a
a sequel data store driver on the class
path well a spring spirit you know it
ideally something should be able to look
at that and scan your class path and say
hey you've got the types that are
required for a sequel data store
connection to be made and really the
only thing we would the only thing such
a thing would need from you is let's say
the URL and the username and password
right because it can look at everything
else and it can go oh I've already got a
connection pool on the class path I've
already got the JDBC driver on the class
path I've already got the JDBC template
and or JPA or mybatis or whatever I've
already got all this required to allow
you to be productive talking to a
Postgres database so all assuming you
give me three little properties like
literally just dock property files
property values like a like a dot ini
Pro property file or a aryama property
file assuming you give me or I or like a
Java properties file right like a Chuck
properties capital P assuming you give
me those three properties those the user
name the URL and the password spring can
can hydrate a data source that's backed
by a connection pool that that is
talking to your your data store and it
can it can stand up the JDBC template or
or JPA and whatever it can take all of
that stuff and turn it into stuff you
can just use you can write your code and
you can tell spring hey I would like a
reference to the to the JPA
entitymanager place and that JPMA ND
manager is already aware of your data
source and it already knows about JTA if
you if you've got the dependencies on
that for that on the classpath etcetera
so it all it already knows about all the
stuff and you get to the business of
just saying I'm gonna write an object
and save it to the database I don't care
about wiring up all that stuff it's just
done for me automatically and that
auto-configuration mechanism technically
is a generic thing right you can take
advantage of it as well so the way it
works is spring starts up there's a
service loader mechanism basically
spring starts up and it looks on the
past path in the meta in factory of any
and all jars in the class path therein
it finds a text file called spring data
factories and there and it finds a line
saying org spring frame boot Auto
configure enable auto configuration
equals and then after that line after
that you know thing that variable name
basically it says equals and then
there's a long list of Java classes and
their comments are limited so you know
my Auto config comma your Auto config
comma whatever and these are the auto
configurations that live on the class
path in these jars and spring boot ships
with you know dozens maybe hundreds of
these little Auto configuration spring
clouds same thing these are Auto
configuration classes that live in these
jars and they're they're automatically
loaded every single one of them is
loaded when your application starts up
which can be a bit I think
nerve-racking for example if you're
starting up a spring boot application
and you see that you've got Auto
configuration there for Kafka but you
don't have coughed in your application
what on earth could that possibly be
doing well we can't afford to just start
creating objects and then have them blow
up with the class not found exceptions
so spring does some very smart things
where we look at these conditions these
are annotations that are added to your
configuration classes that Express
constraints on how these objects are to
be created or the constraints on the
conditions in which these objects to be
are to be created one of those
conditions is hey does this class exist
on the class path
right can we if can I load this class at
all if this class isn't here then don't
bother trying to instantiate this object
that I'm defining here because it will
surely fail I'll get a no class death no
class def error or cos not found
exception yeah hi so so we have some
very smart conditions here we can also
look at other things we can say oh did
the user add this library to the class
path we can detect yep through the use
of this conditional in class we can
detect if there are certain properties
if there's an environment variable set
we can detect if there's another object
art equated and the result is that
spring starts it tries to instantiate
every single one of these Auto
configuration classes that it finds that
serve every kind of conceivable use case
but it only actually launches just a
very small subset of those because we
you know it short circuits evaluation
for the very large majority them because
you don't have the requisite libraries
on the class path so we've gone from a
situation where yeah we we could
configure everything and have complete
flexibility to do whatever we want
yeah to a situation now where I choose
what things I want to put on my class
pass I choose my dependencies and then
spring through these Auto configuration
and conditional annotations will
assemble the framework of an application
which is probably going to do what what
I want to do with the tools that I've
put on the class path absolutely but it
but those conditionals also allow us to
ask questions and and to seek input
basically so we can say okay well we can
configure a javac steps equal that data
source for you and we'll do a good job
we'll give you a connection pool and
it'll be there you know pretty good
settings and all that stuff but we do
need some of your input we need you know
we can't just guess where your Oracle
database lives we you need to tell us
right so we expose a mechanism an
application uh property file and you
specify oh well my spring deck data
source that URL equals this and then the
configuration will read that property
and use that to hydrate the rest of the
machinery right
same thing for same thing for those
conditionals allowing us to look for the
presence of other objects on the in the
application context so if you've already
explicitly provided a beam of type javac
stuff sequel that data source then we'll
just fall back we'll just refer to you
we assume that you know what you're
doing
and you've provided a data source we
won't can we want to configure one for
you right we don't we were not you can
you can have your cake and eat it too
we'll do 90% of work but you provide the
data source so if I've got very specific
requirements for my Hikari connection /
in my production system
I can I can code that up exactly the way
I want a spring we'll use that instead
of its its default Auto configuration
absolutely and and then the other way
that you can exert control over this
configuration is going back to this idea
of you add libraries to the classpath
right those are those are the triggers
that activate functionality in those in
that auto configuration so each time you
add a library that contributes a type
that that one of these Auto
configurations needs each time you add
that to your class path just by adding
it to your maven built then that auto
configuration lights up and it gets run
when your application starts up so
you've got you've got all these
possibilities but unless you have the
types on the prospect they don't they
don't run the implication here is that
you can either add those dependencies
yourself you can go through and add all
the the you know going back to the
Jaypee example you can add the entity
manager you can add an implementation of
JP using hibernate you can add
transaction management and you can
exclude the redundant conflicting
logging libraries you can do it yourself
but since dependency management is key
to the way spring works we've also tried
to simplify that we have this thing
called a starter a starter is a maven
dependency it's a dependency you can use
in maven or SBT or orbital or whatever
yeah but it is it is in turn just it
does nothing but import other
dependencies there's no code in these
starters all it does is it transitively
brings in other dependencies and at
level steps any version conflicts so
that if you have log4j whatever over
here in log4j - over here or whatever we
make sure you get the same version of
all the libraries or you don't have one
that's point one and then point two on
the same class path so the starter
dependencies allow you to say hey I just
want to use the starter called spring
boot starter data JPA and that's it that
that will bring in JPA it'll bring in
hibernate or bring in any manager to
bring in the the right versions of
logging libraries it'll set up
transactions for you to bring in the job
transaction API don't bring in all the
specification type it'll just do all of
that stuff and suddenly you're off to
the races and by virtue of adding that
to a class path
that in turn transit transit Lee brings
in all that other stuff and that in turn
allows the auto-configuration that
detects these types and then configures
jpay for you based on the presence these
types to work so all I've done is
provide my URL username and password and
and I've got an application that is
talking to a database yeah yeah and you
can overwrite you've got you've got
gradients of configuration their
property files might be your first line
of configuration but then you can
provide you can alright objects in the
graph if you want or you can just not
use the auto configuration at all you
can just exclude it right and you can do
everything yourself so it's on a menu of
the starters that are available the
things that I could put into my
application ah it's my second favorite
place in the area start out to spring
that i/o so start that spring Garre Oh
is a is a it's a really amazing piece of
software it's a very it's it's a modest
little application I mean if you look at
the code there's actually quite a bit
going on but what it's doing all it does
is it gives you a one-stop shop for all
these different starters you go there
you get a bunch of check boxes you can
walk down the aisles of the of the
supermarket
spring spring initializer and then you
just choose the dependencies you want
you click a checkbox or you can use a
auto completion search box text box
thing but either way the result is that
you're you're you you specify that I
want JPA check you specify that you want
the support for security and OAuth you
specify that you want the support for
talking to Kafka you specify that you
want a reactive web server you specify
that you want you know service
registration and discovery with the
console or zookeeper or something like
that or an f6 Eureka you specify you
want distributed tracing right do you
write whatever you want there's a
checkbox there let's say that you
specify
let's say that you want to use them
spring boot in a in a Microsoft Azur
application great then go ahead and add
the active directory support there or
want to use it in Google Cloud go ahead
and choose the Google Cloud spanner
dependency there right there's a there's
all sorts of check boxes there you add
them to application hit gym it and it
gives you a little zip file and that zip
file contains a pre
generated maven Palmer
EML beside maven Palmdale XML or a
Gradle that bill bill de grado pas I
give you a skeletal directory structure
source main resources Java and a
skeletal public static void main entry
point class and that's just fit for
import into your favorite IDE now I did
that the long way I went to the start
dot spring nail and I generated a zip
file there but we also have that API
that start to explain and I also powers
a API an HTTP API that you can then use
to generate new projects so if you go to
file new spring the starter project and
IntelliJ or sorry I have spring tool
suite eclipse it's our swing tool suite
is our amazing set of plugins and
extensions on top of eclipse so these
are open source you can just add them to
eclipse distribution and you can go to
the file new starter spring starter
project and it'll it'll in turn run you
through the same wizard the same
dialogue flow that you would have gone
through on startup spring the do it'll
go through that same flow give you the
same exact options and generate a
project that it'll then just input for
you automatically
in spring tool suite ditto for IntelliJ
Ultimate Edition ditto for NetBeans and
the spring boot tools for NetBeans so
you don't have to go to the website you
can actually most of all all major IDs
oh and Visual Studio code as well right
because that's that shares the same
plug-in as the spring tool suite does
the same support for spring boot that we
developed for a spring tool suite also
works in Visual Studio code and in a
demand in Emacs because of this because
all of it is based on language service
right so um okay yeah yeah anything you
want to use so it's right there in the
IDF you file new and I can stand up the
the framework for an application that's
gonna gonna be a restful server or a web
server super service yes urging system
yep absolutely
and it's just but after that you're on
your own you've got a maven project with
a few dependencies that have been added
for you and each dependency corresponds
to one checkbox that you selected back
at the initializer but it is just a
maven project you don't need to spring
you don't need to start that spring that
IO any more to be able to change that
you can add dependencies manually if you
want you can it you can say I want to
add spring boots starter whatever maybe
I forgot one so I can
add the dependi myself that's fine it's
just a maven project and/or a greater
project so I'm not stuck in a place
where I might be with some code
generation no where you know it's a
one-way process and it's it's not easy
to go back and change your mind once
you've made any changes because I'm
working with dependency injection and
ALP and and and just through standard
service api's I'm just working in Java
code yeah yeah but we focused a lot on
features for developers but you know we
what about other interested parties you
when when the when the apps go into into
production and and there and they're in
operation mm-hmm what features has
spring boot got to help the app running
in production ah
well so that's a great point now I'm
surprised I didn't bring it up myself
um springboard is production we it's an
opinionated approached application
development and when I say opinionated
we have a strong opinion about how
applications should run in production
right we want you to have it we already
mentioned some of the obvious things we
don't just give you a data source we
give you a connection pool right we know
that applications are gonna need a
connection pool but I think one of the
more and we also we also give you an
embedded web server right we say rather
than deploying this beautiful piece of
code into this otherwise you know this
other unknown quantity that is an
application server we're gonna embed the
web server in the swing boot app and so
all you need to do to run just bring
what happens to say Java - John right or
even better you can use our example
plugin and they need to dot at /my John
right and either way the result is you
have just a self-contained package that
contains all your dependencies all your
logic or your functionality and even
your web server contains of datasource
your connection pull all that stuff in
this jar that jar is is suitable for
deployment anywhere right so if you have
an opinionated cloud platform like cloud
foundry or Heroku or Google App Engine
although I'm not sure if Google App
Engine does doc jar I think they do but
I'm not sure but either way you should
be able to just take that and run it
without any issues if you want to deploy
it as a dot war you can do that as well
you can deploy it in
to an Apache Tomcat right or or WebLogic
or whatever you want right in a standard
server container will work and I guess
and by the way that goes back to your
your discussion about portability your
question about that I forgot to answer
that yeah you have it in that we can be
built on top of we can run on top of
server containers and things like that
you have portability if you want it
right and we are using JPA which is a
standard right so we support kPa among
you know half a dozen others for sequel
data store access alike alone in that we
have support for those layers you do get
portability if you want it but you're
still working on top of spring so it's
your app and then spring and then the
underlying runtime spring gives you
portability not through the use of
specific types over that's a big part of
it but through through dependency
injection right we we can we can let you
write code that talked to a JDI bound
data source in one environment and then
use a mock data source for test in
another environment right so it's the
same code same object it's just that
because it's expressed its dependency on
atomic steps equal that data source
it doesn't really care where that data
source comes from whether it originates
in a JDI context in in websphere or if
it originates from a in-memory
age to for testing or whatever right
that's the real reason you get
portability so that's just set by the
properties that I've provided when I
when I start the app up well yeah I mean
it something creates a data source in
your application coverage right whether
that springboard or you or whatever but
in your test you don't want to talk to
Oracle right you don't want to talk to
Microsoft sequel server or db2 whatever
your production grade or production
server is you want to just talk to you
like a mock right so I can do your test
so so we we let you write code that is
amenable to being used in other context
without change right you change the
configuration that gets fed into the
creation of the data source and that
results in a days for a sec it's plugged
into object now you know that that's one
of the reasons we have portability is we
have this in direction and the
indirection serves you now if you're
talking about portability you know
there's not there's not two different
versions of spring but nor are there two
different versions two different
versions of log4j so
I'm not sure I don't find that
particular argument persuasive I've ever
I've never understood that whole that
whole idea right there's enough to
different versions of Linux either right
I mean there are but there's not you
know the core that the kernel is you
don't want to diversion to the kernel
you want the same one you want to know
that it's gonna work consistently so
that helps with the deployment the last
thing in deployment the best thing I've
ever have to mention we give you a set
of endpoints called the actuator right
so you add spring boots starter actuator
to your application and actuator as I
understand it is a fixed physics term or
engineering term it describes something
that takes a little bit energy and
turned it into a lot and the actuator in
our case is just a set of operational
management endpoints that surface
information it makes accessible
information about the health of your
application things like metrics things
like the the uptime things like the
health you know of given subsystems in
the application all these things that
you would want to know to understand if
this application needs help if it's sick
and they can't talk to something it
needs to talk to at cetera right who
better to articulate the state and
health of an application than the
application itself is that on top of the
JMX api which is the management
extensions i start some things separate
it's a it's a it's an abstraction so you
can you can turn the actuator data into
j mix in points we can do that for you
automatically you can also turn it into
HTTP endpoints that are mounted in your
web application under force ash by
default its force actuator forward slash
so you've got a force actuator for such
health and you get the health
information or for it's that's actuator
for such metrics and you get the the
metrics information and and then even
there even talking about specific
features you can see you know the the
metrics support i don't want to see my
metrics in a json endpoint in the web
most of the time most the time i want to
publish those metrics to a time series
database right something that got a dead
dog or prometheus or atlas from netflix
or whatever so we have a we have a
project of micrometer or micrometer
which underpins Springs of metrics
support that we did and we developed it
it's generic it doesn't need to be you
can use my comm room without spring but
we use it to let your code talk to
whatever you want
so to publish those metrics that work
for you and you can add you can capture
your own metrics too so I can write my
own timers and counters and have them
published alongside the metrics of CPU
usage and yeah everything else has been
collected about the application yeah I
think that I think CPU and things like
that you know any almost anything will
give you that information these days the
JVM can give you that information your
cloud platform can certainly give you
some that information but I think what
much more meaningfully is is this sort
of key performance indicator kind of
metrics right like um you know how many
transactions do we have per hour or a
per minute or per second how many users
have signed up how many orders have been
fulfilled how many how many messages do
we set do we air or what is the queue
depth of my mic you arrived in the queue
of Kafka Q how many messages do I have
sitting on queue every second right and
that can I can use that information and
say okay well our server is clearly not
keeping up the load is growing let's
let's use the autoscaler on contrary and
tie that to our these metrics and just
spin up a new instance or ten new
instances you can do the same trick with
kubernetes you can do it with whatever
right but that information is there
because we have this metrics collection
abstraction fantastic and there any
other real-time reports that I can get
through the actuators yeah goodness so
there's a dozen or so that come at the
box life I mentioned health and metrics
and there's things like the 30 you can
get a thread dump you can get the heap
dump you can get all sorts of stuff
there but then there's also ones that
get contributed by dependency so other
libraries that have things that are
observable can contribute their own
actuator end points because it is a
framework unto itself so you can
register automatically through the use
of auto configuration these new
endpoints that then get mounted under
for such an actuator so let's say that
you're talking to the spring cloud
config server the spring cloud can fix
servers a is a server that can yet you
can use to sort configuration keys and
values and you can do so in a secure way
if you want as well and it in turn is
backed by a git repository
well that that can fix her itself has
dependencies it's when your client
connects to the config server to read
the keys and values from that config
server your depend
on that and that in turn is dependent on
a git repository I think it you know get
service somewhere you know I know of a
machine I know under SSH or HTTP or
something so when you add the spring
cloud can fix her config server client
to application the starter for that when
you add that in it automatically gives
you a an actuator in point that tells
you about the state of the config sir
itself right because of course you want
to know about that so that's just one
example but there's countless examples
of them throughout the spring ecosystem
of things that add their own actuator
end points right there's even there's
even stuff in the ecosystem at large
people have contributed their own one
that I think it's really brilliant was
that a gentleman a gentleman named
toshiaki Mackey in in Tokyo he created a
graph vis actuator endpoint so it
actually creates a picture of your beams
and the order of the objects in your
application context and how they're
wired together
it's a graph basically that shows you
all the objects and their relationships
okay graph is draws boxes and lines with
arrows between them you got it so so
depending on what the actual class path
is on your production up you can get a
picture of how the spring application
context there's wide the beans together
yeah I mean that's just that's just a
really cool example right you can set
your enter points can be anything they
don't have to be Jason they can be also
two different kind of information kill
yeah yes I like the sound of that and
it's it's it's generally it's generally
inspiring to see what people do with it
because it observe abilities so II you
know it's a big deal when you're
building a monolith application which
you can do with spring moocher but it's
also a big it's a much bigger deal when
you're building a micro service right
micro service systems tend to have lots
of moving parts that's they're
characterized by that if nothing else
right yeah and and so finding an issue
is mag you know much much much more
difficult it's markedly more difficult
in a micro service architecture you know
if you have a null pointer exception in
the monolith it's not hard to say
where's the no pointer I know it's in
the mouse right if I have a memory leak
in the monolith you can ask where's
where's the memory leak well it's in the
monolith
what about a micro service system you
know you have no idea so getting that
visibility is paramount and that's why
it's it's just you just add spring Boop
starter actuator and you've already got
a working set of endpoints you know you
can customize it and maybe unlock or
secure or maybe going the other way you
can secure some of those endpoints with
a few config properly filed values but
out of the box it should be very simple
it's turnkey yeah and right at the start
you talked about yeah consistent way of
developing apps delivering apps
consistent way of running app so I've
got Health metrics Diagnostics
information I'll deliver it in a
consistent way all the instances of all
my micro services yeah and and you can
use that information you mentioned in
the piece briefly a reactive web service
yeah
we a couple years ago on the show we had
Jurgen Haller talking about Spring
Framework five yeah and how we
introduced the reactive streams
programming model yep that's now
included as part of spring booth can you
maybe give us a I know it's a big topic
but could you give us a view of how
spring boot works with the active
streams model yeah so reactive
programming is not a new thing right
it's a it's a it's a it's a relatively
new answer though to a old problem and
the problem is how do we handle more
users and how do we handle more requests
how do we handle more right how do we do
more with the same computer and I think
for a lot of people one important
realization was that there's this lost
opportunity there's this missing
opportunity and all of our programs and
our applications and our systems there's
this missed opportunity because we have
lots of things that are sort of
asynchronous that are latent we wait for
things to happen right and when we're
waiting for things to happen a lot of
times we're sitting there on this thread
waiting for that thing to happen so what
kind of what kind of things do you make
well we might we call it we call it
another web service or we send data to a
database or we do something at CPU bound
but we're doing it on the thread pool
that is being managed
being kept to handle web requests right
okay yeah all these things that are
either network i/o bound or i/o bound or
there sometimes CP on CPU bound but
they're being done in the wrong place
either way we know we've got a finite
number of threads in our web server for
example and we've got this work that
we're doing and that work needs to be as
quick as possible we need to get off
that threaten so our very common thing
is to say okay well I'm gonna move this
work into a separate thing I'm gonna
create a processor that I connect to the
via queue and the whole point of that is
to move work off of my web application
to move it off the main path for web
requests for example right and this is
all problematic be this the reason we do
this is because we're trying to limit
the number of threads that we've got
right threads are expensive on the JVM
actual threads are carrier thread
operating system threads are expensive
yeah on the JVM they're backed by
operating system with threads and those
are those are expensive you know what we
want to do is make more efficient use of
the finite number of threads that we
have in our system and so this gives us
to the idea of cooperative
multi-threading right where you some you
it through some work on your part you
give the runtime a clue or a cue about
whether you're done with a thread or not
so it's slightly more invasive in that
it's not just a generic opaque thread
you're no longer able to say hey run
this code and let me pretend I have the
entire box to myself give me my own
context my own stack and my own thread
of execution right it's not completely
isolated comprar sesang unit now now you
have to give signals to the runtime you
can say hey I'm not using this right now
I'm waiting for something so you can
have the thread back it's yours so just
Park me over here off to the side and
I'll continue in this weight state and
when something happens I'll ask for more
time on the on the on the thread right
cooperative multi-threading is not a new
idea and there's a lot of different ways
to see that support manifest in an
application there's a lot of different
ways to do that
on the JVM and indeed across multiple
languages so Erlang is very famous for
having a very particular actor based
model right that's the a very
opinion a very rigid approach to
concurrency and that's that in turn
inspired things like akka a lot of
different ways to do a cooperative
multi-threading the point is we need
something like that we can't just
continue pretending that I can run
anything I want on a java.lang thread
and there'll be infinite threads we have
a sort of a half step measure that we
can do in 2019 and then we've been able
to do flask ten-odd years where we can
say okay well my application is
intrinsically inefficient it's wasting
time on these threads but I can you know
build a micro service do a 12 factor
style application where I have a little
state as possible in each of the nodes
and I put those you know now that I've
got that kind of application it's cheap
cheap in terms of complexity and turn
and in terms of cost for me to spin up
another instance and then put that
behind a load bouncer right because
there's no state to replicate from one
node to another to keep in consistence
consistent you know so yeah so that
mechanism has allowed us to scale out
and it's a fairly pragmatic middle
ground I think you can you can scale out
and handle more users but you're still
wasting a lot of capacity yeah but
you're not really solving the problem
right yeah so they were the way to do it
is to go to cooperative multi-threading
and reactive programming I think is the
best bet for now for the JVM ok so
reactive programming is this idea that
you have a runtime in a scheduler and
you embrace things that support a
synchronicity you model that
asynchronously using these types that
let you work with streams of data
streams of data that are potentially
unbounded potentially latent and you
have a built-in API it's like a
completable future except that instead
of just getting one value you can get 0
or a trillion or a never-ending stream
of values right also critical to this is
there is the insight that software is is
you know we build software today most of
the time it's a distributed system we're
talking to other things and as soon as
you've got one computer on the network
talking to another you get into this
discussion of back pressure or flow
control client managed flow control I as
the client want to be able to stop or at
least stagger the production of the data
from the producer right otherwise I risk
becoming overwhelmed I risk being you
know denial of service if you will and
so that that's
critical that that flow control is
absolutely the fundamental to weight
distribution systems work it's present
in all network infrastructure all
network programming has to do with this
and yet by the time we get to our
typical application today and the right
tippity-top of the abstraction stack
sitting on top of HTTP and all these
other things we don't even deal with it
anymore we don't even see it there it's
just assumed that it's being handled
hopefully well by some lower-level thing
but as often it's not that's just not
the case and so reactive programming is
both a way of describing asynchronous
streams of data and a way of contending
with or grappling with the realities of
distribution the fact that there are
going to be that you need that had
managed flow control and the fact that
there are going to be errors errors are
not exceptional they're not special
they're just another kind of data and
you should deal with them in a
consistent way there's not a separate
control flow mechanism now that's a
little all of that it's a fairly
abstract what it means for the average
user is that they get an API that looks
kind of like the Java 8 streams API with
some very proud to the differences
namely that you have support for back
pressure you can actually push back on
the producer and and it works fine and
then if you use that if you write your
code using this API using these reactive
streams types that were introduced not
not in spring himself but as the result
of a joint initiative by a number of
different organizations including
pivotal the Eclipse Foundation Netflix
and light Bend nei typesafe all of us
got together and extract out these
common ground types and says reactive
stream specification these types fill a
non-trivial hole in the JDK so so
non-trivial that eventually in Java 9
they were actually packaged you know in
exactly the same way except for the
interface in Java util concurrent dot
flow where flow is a top-level type so
these types are big witness now they're
in the JDK as of Java 9 and so when you
do react to programming you can use
these reactive streams types that were
extracted out into this little specific
this de facto specification and these
different organizations created years
ago or it can use the implementations in
the java 9w token current flow type but
they give you portability they give you
interoperability you can take a reactive
code that runs on spring support for for
reactive API is called Spring web flux
and then spring it in reactor our
projects that supports reactive api's
it's called reactor you can do that
there or you can take a you know you can
take a type from you can take a reactive
stream that's been produced by let's say
raucous fiends right you can use that
with spring Webb flux because they both
speak the same language they both
understand each other the idea of a
reactive stream and our reactive support
these these are this cooperative
multi-threading support that we have in
in spring and in in reactor that support
once you've made that cognitive jump
point to understand and you need to give
the runtime some idea about when you're
no longer using a thread sensors when
you're such as when you're making an
asynchronous Network call like an
asynchronous i/o based Network all that
idea once you've understood then you've
written your code in such a way that
that works some interesting
possibilities open up to you already
today in 2019 there's common write
Kotlin has cobra teams and so
co-routines are it's the idea of okay
well I've got these breaks in the action
in my program these asynchronous Islands
of inactivity where I want to just get
off the thread and wait and I'll let
somebody else use that thread and you
have to if you are willing to teach
Kotlin through its api about these
breaks in the action by by teaching it
about something you basically teach it
about how to adapt this a Singers thing
eight asynchronous thing like a like a
publisher from the reactive stream spec
you teach it how to integrate that with
its own notion of an asynchronous thing
and then it will let you write that code
or let you write this code in a in a way
that looks kind of synchronous it looks
like it's imperative but behind the
scenes the compiler rewrites it so that
the the call stack of a statement that
succeeds or that follows an asynchronous
operation is actually invoked in what
what is basically a callback but to you
from the perspective of the person
writing the code it just looks like you
did state in one two and three one on
you know one two statement ones on one
line statement two and on the second
line saving the three on the on the
third line what's actually happening is
a behind-the-scenes statement to somehow
it does some sort of asynchronous thing
and when the asynchronous thing
completes it then calls statement three
right okay so you write code that looks
yeah it's a call back behind the scenes
it's a that callback that it rehydrates
the state that statement three was
expecting to have when it got to
statement three and including all the
variables in scope and all that
that's called a continuation so I've not
seen that in it complet yeah so it'd be
the reactive streams model it's not some
things that you know you can take on
lightly you know it is a it's a
rewriting the application to use a
different programming model and yep you
know you processing streams in a
functional way yielding control to the
threads just like you saying that Kotlin
now provides some language features that
help you slot that into a more familiar
imperative style right the support
itself the support itself is there's
only one key word that was that into the
language proper it's called suspend
right that one key word is what allows
cotton to understand you have to write
code you have to write you have to you
have to adapt existing you know
asynchronous types like like a reactive
stream you teach Kotlin how to adapt
that into his own your own idea and then
it'll just work so you can everything
you understand and then activate guys
now you can use encodings right so we
already get we've already done that they
have a separate project that doesn't
live in the common language itself it's
just a separate project maintained by
dippings that contains all these
adapters so if you want to use reactor
or our next OVA or futures or whatever
there's all these adapters that teach
the common runtime think of these a
singers things that has co-routine so I
think if you got an example of in a
simple web application yeah well
possibly if we got one I'll definitely
put it in in the show notes but sure
Gharib calm spring tips this is spring -
tips and it's Kor Oh UTI any yes it's a
get up comm spring - tips for such go
routines I even just did a video on that
but the but the benefit of that cook
models that if you're using Carmen and
you know it's a lovely language I know
why you wouldn't
if using Kotlin you can write code that
takes advantage of these reactive api's
but - you just looks like you're just
saying okay the results of this query
equals this and it's not a bits not up
it's not a promise or a completable
future or whatever it's just the actual
object and it looks like you just got
the object from a direct call and it
looks like you blocked but behind the
scenes it's actually an asynchronous way
that call and the the method invocation
pauses and actually stops working and it
Heike it packages up the state into this
continuation and the continuation gets
invoked on a callback in a separate
thread later on it is absolutely magic
you know amazing okay I'm definitely
going to take a look is the reactive
model is something you know it needs to
be used everywhere of all the components
in us of typical Enterprise stack and
they are now available with reactive API
so definitely not know so one of the
biggest roadblocks I mean if you want to
build a web application the servlet API
doesn't really support any secret it
supports a async request and response
but for example resolution of session
information cookies that kind of stuff
that's not reactive which is fine you're
probably that's probably not going to
notice it so we actually have an adapter
that runs spring web flex on top of
existing service API so that's that's an
option but we just prefer by default if
you do spring boot you add spring boots
start a web flux al UX what you get is a
a reactive web runtime based on MIDI
that gets added to your class path and
that and that just works by default
there's no servlet API there at all
no dependency there and it's you know
optimized for being a reactive web
runtime but then and I think that was
actually easy thing right providing a
brand-new web runtime is the easy part
the hard part is these more traditional
sort of enterprise II things like sequel
data stores or even dev source in
general right not all data stores
provide asynchronous i/o based drivers
and so it makes no it gives us it gives
nobody an advantage to
uselessly adapt or provide a facade on
top of a blocking API that makes it look
like it's reactive well actually being
asynchronous right now if if I call into
JDBC
JDBC is a fundamentally blocking API it
doesn't matter how much I adapt that you
kind of look like it it's still gonna
waste a thread behind the scenes
underneath the hood there right I
remember the I've listened to the show
with you can holler again recently and
he was talking about how a database
transaction by its very nature is not
reactive and it is there to give lock
rows in tables and make you
wait until the work is done right
exactly so that so that G jdbc is a very
common one but even like neo4j up until
just yesterday when they made public
their reactive neo4j driver right and
and their spring data module up until
then there was no no there was no
asynchronous and non walking version of
neo4j potato for most of these different
data stores to be fair Couchbase i think
was the first one time trees had a a
synchronous i/o a reactive driver
actually their implementation by default
is built on a signal so when it came
time to build the spring data adapter
for that the spring data intubation but
it wasn't very difficult at all because
it was already natively reactive do for
MongoDB they were very early they had a
very good very workable very usable
asynchronous i/o driver and that was one
of our first supported spring data
modules to support asynchronous reactive
programming Cassandra and Redis all
suits very shortly but sequel has always
been the sort of thing that that people
wanted to use because of course that
sized I think that's still you know the
prevailing thing I think if you ask any
group of developers you'll find that the
prevailing plurality at least is a it's
a sequel so we have a project called our
2d BC our TBC is an abstraction it's an
SPI that provides in a reactive approach
to sequel integration and it's that type
of spring it's just a separate project
it's written in terms of the low-level
reactive schemes types there's no
dependency on reactor or akka streams or
marks Java or any of these other
reactive runtimes and that in turn
provides a you know art project arts are
TVC internships with a number of drivers
those that implement this spi so we've
got a box support for posters and SPI is
a service provider in space right it's a
way yeah people to adapt to a standard
interface for dealing with something
like a relational database okay and it
just like GDC right at JDC it's just a
set of interfaces but you need an
implementation for that to be usable and
meaningful so we have an SPI we have yes
parent have a number of implementations
of which we have PostgreSQL Microsoft
sequel server and each - there's a third
party one called JA sync Jas ymc and
that
third party project and they have an
imputation for my sequel and I can tell
you there's almost all the major
databases with which you want to connect
I don't know what Oracle but I know that
almost all of the major ones and you can
imagine wanting to connect it already
solve media ones I want to connect to
half or are going to have soon work
being done or have already done work on
an hour TBC drivers so there's a large
coalition of fingers I want to support
that's right that we're I'm work on this
so I think it's exciting right now it's
a like I said it's limited to those for
right now practically speaking so if
you're not in that group then reactive
program it may not be for you right
that's fair if you're not using
Cassandra Redis calculate some on TV and
now neo4j it may not be for you that's
fair - right you can still use these
things from reactive applications but
you're gonna end up blocking threads so
we have to scale out those interactions
by adding more threads which is sort of
countries of point right yeah exactly
but with two DBC or two DBC it's the
it's a really reactive relational
database connectivity so are two you see
okay yeah that's bridging but
transactional processing the databases
whether with a reactive model well so
that group that brings up another great
question which is yeah so you can do
transactions in our TVC and you can also
do transactions in MongoDB and actually
we can do transactions in both our TBC
and among going to be in the reactive
versions as well so the question then is
how do we do transactions in a seroma
how do we model that that innate the
interesting thing in a unified way so in
Spring Framework we've long had this
idea of a platform transaction manager
which is a low-level a type with height
which has three methods it allows you to
get a transaction it allows you to
commit the transaction or to roll it
back and that unit that abstraction has
a number of implications there must be
dozens of them at this point that talk
to anything that you can imagine
modeling as having a transaction so JTA
you know drug transaction API for
distributions accident yeah JPA has its
own concept of resource local
transactions JDBC has its own concept of
resource local transactions ditto for
JMS ditto for J do you know you might
remember J do ya see no forum hibernate
itself property node specifically ditto
for Kafka ditto for
rabbitmq Jennifer Neal Ford
you know for you know this this unending
list of things that have known concept
of resource local transactions we have
implementations of that interface for
all these different things and if you
want you can use an implementation of
that interface in your spring code you
can then use that with something called
the transaction template and the
transaction template lets you run code
inside of lambda in the context of
transaction if there are any errors or
exceptions then the transaction is
rolled back otherwise it's committed for
you and you can go step further you can
instead of enclosing a transactional
logic instead of do marketing that
transaction using this transaction
template you can use the transactional
declarative annotation on your method
and that'll demarcate our transaction
around the it'll enclose your method in
the in the in a demarcated transaction
for you automatically that interface has
been there since the very beginning of
spring it's one of the most useful
things of spring and so we were looking
for a way to support that same kind of
convenience in the transactional world
but here as you've just alluded to
things are quite difficult because the
the assumption with the platform
transaction manager is that you've got
thread-local storage well of course as
transactions jump the thread of
execution all quite often as we as
reactive transactions jump thread of
execution quite often they go from one
thread to another in the same
transaction
yes gonna get off the thread as soon as
possible right and so it no longer makes
sense to stash that just state the the
storage for the transaction it can't be
associated with just one particular
thread because I no longer is the
prevailing truth it's not true that one
thread will always be the one being used
for a transaction so we needed some way
to to recreate that we created this
we've created a reactive transaction
manager interface and the first two
implementations that we have already are
for our TVC for you know sequel data
store access and for MongoDB right okay
now you can use it you now you can use a
reactive transaction manager and what
that does is behind the scenes it's
using a mechanism in reactor to
propagate context tool information in
the pipeline itself in a reactive
pipeline itself so it's storage that's
associated with the pipeline and then
that gets propagated from one thread to
another for you automatically okay it
you can think of it as a dictionary or a
context I get to add it to each pipeline
and you can you can use that and we use
behind-the-scenes as a generic mechanism
for propagation of security information
credentials that kinda stuff context
rather in a principal information in
spring security reactive spring security
we use that for for distributed tracing
with spring cloud sleuth and things like
zip get read and open tracing that you
know automatic trace reactive requests
that way as well so every time you you
you control every time you get a car but
this is context that's carrying deputy
information that previously you could
have just stood in a thread local right
but now he's got to be managed all the
way through the stream processing well I
mean you don't you don't end up having
the manager right spring doesn't for you
but yeah it's something that's true
before something had to make sure you
stat you started and cleared the throne
local as well so the the point of spring
is doing that for you in the case of the
third local and it's now doing it for
you in the case of this context object
and it's again it's a generic
abstraction the context is something you
can use as well I did a swing tips video
for example on heavily heavily heavily
like almost entirely inspired by Seaborn
Bosley as a amazing blog demonstrating
how to do how to bridge MDC with
reactive right how do I take a log
context and I'm gonna have to wrap yes
transaction for example so yeah so we
can you can do that as well using
context it's just generic a mechanism
that allows you to do that and we do
that for transaction management now so
we have a reactive transaction manager
and then we have a transactional
operator which is more or less similar
to the transaction template but it's an
and it's analogous for the reactive
world and I did a spring tips video
introducing all of this as well just
recently if for those of you orange did
it if that's another one for the show
notes will follow follow follow up on
that separately and we talked about we
touched on some issues there with spring
cloud sleuth take you know huge topics I
say bring security we mentioned you know
we could do another show happy job so I
think I might take you up on that that's
a great place to wrap up I think cool
yeah so where would you quickly
recommend people go for resources about
spring boot oh dear
so the best resources are of course
spring that I out for that guy
these are 10 to 15 minute long
digestible bits of information they're
little little things that you can read
that I'll teach you one little trick
like how to build a simple REST API and
it's not like it's not everything you
need to know about rest okay
it's just how to make spring boot create
a simple HTTP endpoint that you can then
use as the basis for your explorations
of rest with spring boot it's the make
it wiggle factor right ever there's
dozens of these other recipes I wanna
but I want to send a message to took-off
Kiwanis I want to use a circuit breaker
I want to do centralized configuration
I'm gonna do hola whatever there's a
bunch of these guys right that's one
great place I have a plainness called
spring tips where every Wednesday I
published a new video before we got on
the line I was making sure that that got
uploaded for today's installment and
it's a bi tly for - spring - tips -
playlist I also do a podcast every
Friday that's not as nice as this one of
course but it's a it's available we're
fine wherever fine podcasts are pervade
called a beautiful podcast excellent the
documentation is legendarily good and
also if you want to contribute dear
audience we love people that want to
contribute to the open-source world we
have in most of our projects we have in
the github issue tracker
but if projects that are labeled open
for feedback or open ideal for
contribution or whatever these are these
are things that are ideal for people who
are aspiring to become people in the
network in the community the open source
community and they're not sure where to
start and it can be kind of overwhelming
to try and influence a giant project
liking in the spring projects right if
you want something where it's an easy
place to put your feet in the water and
we're gonna be very happy to help you
there's a bunch of these issues just
find one say hey I'd like to tackle this
and we'll support you on that more we'd
love to see you become a contributing
member of the project people I said all
the time fantastic and then last one
more plug I have a book I'm working on
called reactive spring you can go to
lean pub comm and it's a react at you
and I'm just gonna react to spring that
IO and you'll you'll find the link to
the book you can buy it now it's already
access and you're entitled to the full
book the final book when it's done and
you can feed back and give me
contributions
okay and we can watch it as you
completes it yeah exactly and so it's a
it's a early it's an agile
for publishing books this is my this is
the first book I'm self-publishing and
it's a it's really been a really amazing
experiment I've never done this before I
didn't know how exciting this could be I
knew I thought it might be I know how
exciting it is to get people to be
interested in your software and to get
them interested in get on get up but
this is that same sort of process but
for books and I actually write the book
and release it using software tools
right it's a continuous delivery
platform a continuous delivery pipeline
that I built to publish this book so
it's um it's very iterative a very very
interesting experience brilliant okay
great well Josh leave these to say thank
you for coming on the show oh well thank
you so much for having me
absolute pleasure yeah it's been a real
privilege it's been it's been great fun
talking to you you know my way so thank
you this is Simon cross leaf for
software engineering radio and thank you
for listening thanks for listening at se
radio an educational program brought to
you by Archer police software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack channel at SC
radio.com you can also email us at team
@ SC - radio net this and all other
episodes of se radio is licensed under
Creative Commons license 2.5 thanks for
listening